Guide to the Afrika Bambaataa hip hop archive, circa 1972-2016.
Bambaataa, Afrika hip hop archive,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Afrika Bambaataa hip hop archive, circa 1972-2016.
8094
Afrika Bambaataa, 1957-
600 cubic feet.
Vinyl records and other A/V Recordings, Financial Records, Manuscripts, Memorabilia, Photocopies, Photographs, Printed Materials, Publications.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Approximately 40,000 sound recordings representing Bambaataa's music collection from the 1970s to the present. The archive also includes books, documents, and files relating to the founding and spread of the Universal Zulu Nation; and videos, papers, and clothing.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Afrika Bambaataa is an American disc jockey, singer, and songwriter from the South Bronx, New York. Often called the “Godfather” of Hip Hop, Bambaataa has helped to define Hip Hop since it emerged in the South Bronx in the 1970s. One of a handful of Hip Hop's 1970s originators, Bambaataa gave Hip Hop its name, and was the first to define its core artistic elements - DJing, rapping, break dancing, and graffiti art - under one cultural umbrella. His cultural organization, the Universal Zulu Nation, has helped to spread Hip Hop culture throughout the world. His genre-defining 1982 song "Planet Rock" and subsequent electro-funk tracks have become icons of hip-hop and electronic music. In 2007 he was nominated for induction into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Approximately 40,000 sound recordings representing Bambaataa's music collection from the 1970s to the present. The archive also includes books, documents, and files relating to the founding and spread of the Universal Zulu Nation; and videos, papers, and clothing.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Afrika Bambaataa, 1957-; Universal Zulu Nation (Organization)
Subjects:
African American youth -- Social life and customs.; Disc jockeys.; Electronic music.; Funk (Music).; Hip-hop.; Hip-hop -- Influence.; Hip-hop -- History. -- United States; Music -- Social aspects.; Race relations.; Rap (Music); Rap (Music) -- Political aspects.; Rap musicians.; Hip-hop -- New York.; Rap (Music) -- New York.; Hip-hop; Rap (Music); Rap musicians; Social history
Places:
Bronx (New York, N.Y.) -- Social conditions -- 20th century.; New York (State) -- New York; New York (State) -- Bronx; United States
Form and Genre Terms:
History
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Access to collection restricted until completion of processing, with the exception of vinyl records that have been individually cataloged.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Manuscripts
a. School Papers and Assignments
b. Africa Trip
c. Soul Scrapbooks and Music Writing
d. Notebooks and Miscellaneous Manuscripts
e. Lyrics and Poems
f. Bronx River Neighborhood Center
g. Phone and Contact Lists
Series II. Flyers
Series III. Photographs
Series IV. Personal Papers
a. Personal Papers
b. Press About Bambaataa
c. Catalogs and Mail
Series V. Universal Zulu Nation Documents
a. Infinity Lessons
b. Administration
Series VI. Stage Costumes and Clothing
Series VII. Periodicals and Publications
a. Small Press Publications
b. Periodicals
c. Publications from 3410 De Reimer Ave. Bronx, NY
d. Other Publications
Series VIII. Moving images and audio recordings
a. Video cassettes
a. Audio cassettes
Series IX. Music collection
12 inch vinyl
Sureshots and altered/obscured
Numbered by Bambaataa
Annotated, not numbered (Alphabetical by artist)
A-D
E-H
I-L
L-O
P-S
T-Z
Numbers, unknown and various
Second alpha sequence
Cataloged individually
Not annotated (Alphabetical by artist)
A
B
C
D
E
F
G
H
I
J
K
L
M
N
O
P
Q
R
S
Afrika Bambaataa recordings
Renegades of Rhythm Tour
Test pressings and white labels (not yet cataloged)
Compilations (not yet cataloged)
7 inch vinyl
Numbered (not yet cataloged)
Annotated not numbered (not yet cataloged)
No annotations (not yet cataloged)
Acetates and lacquer discs
Cassettes (not yet cataloged)
CDs (not yet cataloged)
Series X. Ephemera
CONTAINER LIST
- Series IX. Music Collection
  - 12 inch Vinyl
    - Not annotated
      Series contains vinyl discs that are either not annotated or the annotations are small and were missed during the sorting of discs. While some effort was taken to bring together piences that were dense in copy-specific track preferences. These items are arranged in alphabetical order by artists’ last name or the name of the group. Each letter of the alphabet has a subseries. Compilations, soundtracks, and other albums with various artists are in subseries together. Artists and groups whose names start with a number are in a separate subseries. Most artists are alphabetized under the name they are most well-known as (e.g. Puff Daddy; Prince; Fela). The variations of names are contained in the Creator field. In a few cases, however, artists’ aliases were unknown, and they may have been listed under two different artist names.
      - Q
        - Q Base - Tango beat, 1990; SR-23501; Q Base (Box 401)
          Catalog # DFC 036; A-side Matrix # DFC 036 A
          DFC
          Bologna, Italy
        - Q-Pid - My Latin lover, 1986; SR-23502; Q-Pid; Nikki Q (Box 401)
          Catalog # LEFT 1T; A-side Matrix # LEFT 1 T A1
          Rhythm King Records
          London, United Kingdom
        - Q-Pid - My Latin lover, 1986; SR-23503; Q-Pid; Nikki Q (Box 401)
          In same jacket as # SR-23504. Multiple copies. Promo
          Catalog # SUN 434; A-side Matrix # A-SUN-434A
          Sunnyview
          New York, New York
        - Q-Pid - My Latin lover, 1986; SR-23504; Q-Pid; Nikki Q (Box 401)
          In same jacket as # SR-23503. Multiple copies. Promo
        - Qadeer - My city, 2004; SR-23505; Qadeer (Box 401)
          Catalog # unknown; A-side Matrix # 9311-Qadeer-1 (A) S-56466
          Triple P Records
          Nevada
        - Quad City DJ's - Space jam, 1996; SR-23506; Quad City DJ's (Box 401)
          In same jacket as # SR-23507. Multiple copies. Promo
          Catalog # DMD 2332; A-side Matrix # ST-DM-85167-85166
          Warner Sunset Records
          Los Angeles, California
        - Quad City DJ's - Space jam, 1996; SR-23507; Quad City DJ's (Box 401)
          In same jacket as # SR-23506. Multiple copies. Promo
        - Quad City DJ's - C'mon n' ride it (the train), 1996; SR-23508; Quad City DJ's (Box 401)
          Promo
          Catalog # DMD 2279; A-side Matrix # STDM-95651 A1
          Big Beat Records
        - Quad City DJ's - Summer jam, 1997; SR-23509; Quad City DJ's (Box 401)
          Catalog # 0-95571; A-side Matrix # ST-DM-86628-86629-83 664-1
        - Quadrant Six - Body mechanic; Pipeline, SR-23510; Quadrant Six; Johnston, Bruce (Box 401)
          Catalog # 0.00138888888888889; A-side Matrix # 0-02-A
          Rated "X" Records
        - Quadrant Six - Body mechanic; She's tasty, 1996; SR-23511; Quadrant Six (Box 401)
          Catalog # HCL 2292; A-side Matrix # HCL-2292 A (HCL)
          The Perfect Beat Records
          Miami, Florida
        - Quadrant Six - The lone wolf, 1983; SR-23512; Quadrant Six; Simmons, Kenny (Box 401)
          Catalog # DMD 655; A-side Matrix # STDM-45055-6
          Atlantic Recording Corporation
        - Quando Quango - Love tempo, 1984; SR-23513; Quando Quango (Box 401)
          Annotated. Promo
          Catalog # OFNY-5; A-side Matrix # OFNY-5-A
          Of Factory New York
        - Quando Quango - Love tempo, 1983; SR-23514; Quando Quango (Box 401)
          Annotated.
          Catalog # FBN 23; A-side Matrix # FBN 23 A
          Factory Benelux
          Belgium
        - Quartz - Naked love (just say you want me), 1991; SR-23515; Quartz; Carroll, Dina (Box 401)
          Catalog # ITM 412; A-side Matrix # ITM 412A-1U-1-2
          Mercury Records
        - Quaye, Finley - Spiritualized, 2000; SR-23516; Quaye, Finley (Box 401)
          Catalog # EAS 16446; A-side Matrix # XSS 16446 A
          Epic
          United Kingdom
        - Que - Street game; Dope game, SR-23517; Que; Jadakiss; Bun B (Box 401)
          Catalog # unknown; A-side Matrix # L-13144MA
          Dee Money Records
          Atlanta, Georgia
        - Queen - Another one bites the dust, 1998; SR-23518; Queen; Jean, Wyclef; Pras; Free (Box 401)
          Catalog # PRO-A-5105; A-side Matrix # PRO A 5105-A-GLI
          Dreamworks Records
          Universal City, California
        - Queen - Radio ga ga, 1984; SR-23519; Queen (Box 401)
          Catalog # V-8575; A-side Matrix # V-8575-99195-Z1
          Capitol Records
          Hollywood, California
        - Queen - Flash Gordon (original soundtrack music), 1980; SR-23520; Queen (Box 401)
          Catalog # 5E-518-A; A-side Matrix # 5E-518A-5 AR(SH) TD ESR + + R.T. 543 B-15450 +
          Elektra
        - Queen - The game, 1980; SR-23521; Queen (Box 401)
          Catalog # 5E-513-A SP; A-side Matrix # 5E-513-A SH + SLM + 423 B-15094 0-1SM2-2
        - Queen Latifah - Latifah's had it up 2 here, 1991; SR-23522; Queen Latifah (Box 401)
          Catalog # TB 506; A-side Matrix # AE 282191A
          Tommy Boy Records
        - Queen Latifah - Ladies first, 1989; SR-23523; Queen Latifah; Love, Monie (Box 401)
          In same jacket as # SR-23524. Multiple copies.
          Catalog # GEET 23Y; A-side Matrix # GEET 23Y B1
          Gee Street
        - Queen Latifah - Ladies first, 1989; SR-23524; Queen Latifah; Love, Monie (Box 401)
          In same jacket as # SR-23523. Multiple copies.
          Catalog # GEET 23Y; A-side Matrix # GEET 23Y 131
        - Queen Latifah - Order in the court, 1998; SR-23525; Queen Latifah (Box 401)
          Catalog # 374630895-1; A-side Matrix # 374630895-1A
          Motown
        - Queen Latifah - Fly girl; Nature of a sista', 1991; SR-23526; Queen Latifah (Box 401)
          Catalog # TB 991 A; A-side Matrix # TB-991 A
        - Queen Latifah - All hail the queen, 1989; SR-23527; Queen Latifah (Box 401)
          In same jacket as # SR-23528. Multiple copies.
          Catalog # GEE A5; A-side Matrix # GEEA5-A
        - Queen Latifah - All hail the queen, 1989; SR-23528; Queen Latifah (Box 401)
          In same jacket as # SR-23527. Multiple copies.
        - Queen Latifah - How do I love thee?, 1992; SR-23529; Queen Latifah (Box 401)
          Catalog # TB 515; A-side Matrix # 0-515-A
        - Queen Latifah - Order in the court, 1998; SR-23530; Queen Latifah (Box 401)
          In same jacket as # SR-23531. Different discs. Promo
        - Jay-Z - 99 problems, 2004; SR-23531; Jay-Z (Box 401)
          In same jacket as # SR-23530. Different discs. Promo
          Catalog # DEFR 16058-1; A-side Matrix # B0002484-11-A1
          Roc-A-Fella Records
        - Queen Latifah - Fly girl; Nature of a sista', 1991; SR-23532; Queen Latifah (Box 401)
        - Queen Latifah - Black hand side (remix), 1994; SR-23533; Queen Latifah (Box 401)
          Catalog # 374631196-1; A-side Matrix # 37463 1196-1A
        - Queen Latifah - Mama gave birth to the soul children, 1990; SR-23534; Queen Latifah; De La Soul (Box 401)
          Catalog # TB 957; A-side Matrix # TB-957 A
        - Queen Latifah - Paper, 1998; SR-23535; Queen Latifah (Box 401)
          Catalog # 374633006-1; A-side Matrix # 374633006-1-A
        - Queen Latifah - Latifah's had it up 2 here, 1991; SR-23536; Queen Latifah (Box 401)
          Catalog # TB 506; A-side Matrix # 0-506 A
        - Queen Latifah - It's alright, 1997; SR-23537; Queen Latifah (Box 401)
          In same jacket as # SR-23538. Multiple copies.
          Catalog # TB 402; A-side Matrix # OP402A
        - Queen Latifah - It's alright, 1997; SR-23538; Queen Latifah (Box 401)
          In same jacket as # SR-23537. Multiple copies.
        - Queen Latifah - Wrath of my madness, 1988; SR-23539; Queen Latifah (Box 401)
          Catalog # TB 916; A-side Matrix # TB-916-A
        - Queen Latifah - Wrath of my madness, 1988; SR-23540; Queen Latifah (Box 401)
        - Queen Mother Rage - Slipping into darkness, 1990; SR-23541; Queen Mother Rage (Box 401)
          Catalog # 3-4004-0-DJ; A-side Matrix # 3-4004-0 RE1 A
          Cardiac Records
        - Queen Mother Rage - Vanglorious law, 1990; SR-23542; Queen Mother Rage (Box 401)
          Catalog # 3-8001-1; A-side Matrix # 3-8001-1 A2- 1-1
        - Queen Pen - Conversations with Queen (disc one), 2001; SR-23543; Queen Pen (Box 401)
          In same jacket as # SR-23544. Double album. Promo
          Catalog # 440 013 785-1; A-side Matrix # 440-013-785-1 440-014-334-1A
        - Queen Pen - Conversations with Queen (disc two), 2001; SR-23544; Queen Pen (Box 401)
          In same jacket as # SR-23543. Double album. Promo
          Catalog # 440 013 785-1; A-side Matrix # 440-013-785-1 440-014-335-1A
        - Queen Pen - It's true, 1998; SR-23545; Queen Pen (Box 401)
          Catalog # INT8P-6399; A-side Matrix # INT8P-6399-A-1
          Interscope Records
          Santa Monica, California
        - Queen Pen - Man behind the music, 1997; SR-23546; Queen Pen (Box 401)
          In same jacket as # SR-23547. Multiple copies. Promo
          Catalog # INT8P 6228; A-side Matrix # INT8P-6228-A-rel-1
        - Queen Pen - Man behind the music, 1997; SR-23547; Queen Pen (Box 401)
          In same jacket as # SR-23546. Multiple copies. Promo
        - Queen Samantha - Queen Samantha 2, 1979; SR-23548; Queen Samantha (Box 401)
          Catalog # Marlin-2230; A-side Matrix # MAR-2230-A
          Marlin
          Hialeah, Florida
        - Queen Samantha - Close your eyes; Summer dream, 1983; SR-23549; Queen Samantha (Box 401)
          Catalog # MT-109; A-side Matrix # MT-109-A
          Megatone Records
          San Fransisco, California
        - Queensrÿche - Speak the word, 1988; SR-23550; Queensrÿche (Box 401)
          Catalog # SPRO-04194; A-side Matrix # SPRO 04194 Z1 B-33621 23258
          EMI USA
        - Quest For Exellence - Family of people, 1990; SR-23551; Quest For Exellence (Box 401)
          Catalog # LICT 034; A-side Matrix # LICT-034-A1
          Republic Records
        - Questionmark Asylum - Hey lookaway, 1995; SR-23552; Questionmark Asylum (Box 401)
          Catalog # 07863 64302-1; A-side Matrix # 07863-64302-1-A-1
          Kaper Records
        - Questionmark Asylum - Get with you; I'd rather be with you, 1995; SR-23553; Questionmark Asylum (Box 401)
          Catalog # RDAB 64387-1; A-side Matrix # RDAB-64387-1-A
        - Questions - Tear soup, 1983; SR-23554; Questions (Box 401)
          Catalog # KOBX 705; A-side Matrix # KOBX 705-A1
          Respond Records
        - Quick - Zulu, 1981; SR-23555; Quick (Box 401)
          Catalog # 4Z9 02433; A-side Matrix # 4Z9-02433-4-AB
          Pavillion
        - Quick - Zulu, 1981; SR-23556; Quick (Box 401)
          Catalog # 4Z9 02433; A-side Matrix # 4Z9-02433-3-AB
        - Quick - Rhythm of the jungle, 1982; SR-23557; Quick (Box 401)
          Catalog # 49-02809; A-side Matrix # XSS170019-1A
        - Quick Hit Boys - Bring it outside, 2001; SR-23558; Quick Hit Boys (Box 401)
          Catalog # unknown; A-side Matrix # BRINGITOUTSIDE-A
          Quick Hit Records
          United States
        - Quicksand - Manic compression, 1995; SR-23559; Quicksand (Box 401)
          Catalog # PR12 6831-1; A-side Matrix # PRLP-6831-1A
          Revelation Records
        - Quindon - It's you that's on my mind, 1996; SR-23560; Quindon (Box 402)
          Catalog # SPRO-11087; A-side Matrix # SPRO-11087-A
          Virgin Records America, Inc.
        - Quinton - Quinton's here; I'm not an MC, 1994; SR-23561; Quinton (Box 402)
          Catalog # TB 604; A-side Matrix # TB-604 A
        - Quinton - Quinton's here; I'm not an MC, 1994; SR-23562; Quinton (Box 402)
          Catalog # TB 619; A-side Matrix # TB-619 A KL
          Fathouse Wreckords
        - Quo - Huh what?, 1994; SR-23563; Quo; Redman (Box 402)
          Catalog # EAS 6013; A-side Matrix # XSS-6013A-1A
          MJJ Music
        - Quo - Quo funk, 1994; SR-23564; Quo; Brownstone; Vicious (Box 402)
          Catalog # 49 77802; A-side Matrix # XSS-77802-A
        - Quruli - World's end supernova EP, 2009; SR-23565; Quruli (Box 402)
          Catalog # FMR-134; A-side Matrix #
          Face The Music Records
          Japan
        - QSR - Washed out, 2000; SR-23566; QSR (Box 402)
          Catalog # UNIR-20307-1; A-side Matrix # UNIR-20307 1A
          Universal Records
        - Q.T. - Want some, get some, 1981; SR-23567; Q.T. (Box 402)
          Catalog # MM 100 AA; A-side Matrix # MM-100 AA-REI-1-1 PRC-C MM-101
          M & M Records
        - Qwilo - Dirty motha, 1997; SR-23568; Qwilo; Felix Da Housecat; Crouch, Lynn (Box 402)
          Catalog # FESX 29; A-side Matrix # FESX 29 A1
          Manifesto
        - Q - The voice of Q, 1982; SR-30878; Q (Box 402)
          Catalog # PWR-2007; A-side Matrix # PWR-2007-A
          Philly World Records
          Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
        - Q-Burns Abstract Message - Shame, 2001; SR-30879; Q-Burns Abstract Message (Box 402)
          Catalog # ASW 38797; A-side Matrix # ASW-38797 A1
          Astralwerks
        - Queens Brooklyn Connection - Back to school; (I'm) just adjustin' my mike (side two), 1980; SR-30959; Queens Brooklyn Connection; Q.B.C. (Box 147)
          Test pressing, acetate.
          Catalog # V-15431; A-side Matrix #
        - Quartz - Naked love (just say you want me), 1991; SR-30960; Quartz; Carroll, Dina (Box 147)
          London, England
        - Queen Samantha - Queen Samantha 2, 1979; SR-30961; Queen Samantha (Box 147)